Guide to the Sergeant Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Sergeant family papers
1751-1953
MS 806
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.92
(6 boxes)
Correspondence and other papers of several members of the Sergeant family of Massachusetts and Connecticut. Major correspondents include George Sergeant (1822-), of Northampton, Massachusetts; his sister, Catharine Sedgwick Sergeant De Forest, married to Dr. Henry A. De Forest; and his daughter, Catharine De Forest Sergeant (1848-). The collection contains correspondence on female education in Syria and education of women in the United States. Later letters, mainly in the 1870s, describe the experiences of women as students and as teachers in Princeton, New Jersey, Chicago, West Haven, Connecticut and elsewhere. Also includes family photographs and daguerreotypes.
Sergeant family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of Katharine S. White, 1977-1978.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence and other papers of several members of the Sergeant family of Massachusetts and Connecticut. Major correspondents include George Sergeant (1822-), of Northampton, Massachusetts; his sister, Catharine Sedgwick Sergeant De Forest, married to Dr. Henry A. De Forest; and his daughter, Catharine De Forest Sergeant (1848-). The collection contains correspondence on female education in Syria and education of women in the United States. Later letters, mainly in the 1870s, describe the experiences of women as students and as teachers in Princeton, New Jersey, Chicago, West Haven, Connecticut and elsewhere.
Biographical / Historical
George Sergeant was a resident of Northampton, Massachusetts and Seymour, Connecticut.
Catharine Sedgwick Sergeant De Forest (approximately 1817-1896), sister of George Sergeant, was born in Stockbridge, Massachusetts. She was a descendent of John Sergeant (1710-1749, Yale 1729), a missionary to Native Americans in western Massachusetts who established a boarding school for Native American children in Stockbridge. De Forest and her husband, Henry De Forest (Yale 1832, MD 1835), established and administered the first school for girls in Syria in the 1840s and early 1850s, where Henry De Forest was stationed as a medical missionary. John W. De Forest, author, also spent several years at the school in Syria.
Arrangement
The material is arranged as received from the donor.
Education; Families; Women -- Education -- Syria; Connecticut; Middle East; New England; New Haven (Conn.); Clergy; Educators; Women teachers; De Forest, Catharine Sedgwick Sergeant, 1819-1896; De Forest, Henry A.; Fowler, John; Sergeant, Catharine De Forest; Sergeant, Charles Spencer, 1852-; Sergeant, Elliott; Sergeant, George; Sergeant, Lydia Ann Clark, -1863; Sergeant, Mary Louise
- Inventory
  - Genealogical and biographical notes and photographs regarding the De Forest, Partridge, Quincy, and Sergeant families, 1878-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Also includes two photographs of a Chippendale side chair.
  - Genealogical notes regarding the Clark, Hadley, Partridge, and Sergeant families, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Also includes a biographical note on Erastus Sergeant (1742-1814).
  - Financial records, correspondence, photographs, and artifacts, 1796-1841 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes deeds, accounts, receipts, promissory notes, and credit orders payable in kind of Dr. Oliver Partridge; a letter to Sewall Sergeant; a photograph of an unidentified woman; and the red leather pouch of Dr. Oliver Partridge, in which the folder contents were stored.
  - Genealogical notes, legal and financial documents, and correspondence, 1751-1847 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes genealogical notes regarding the Clap, Clark, Sergeant, and Williams families; a copy of the last will and testament of Dr. Oliver Partridge; deeds, quit claims, plans, and maps regarding division of property in Partridgeville; apothecary notes and note book of Dr. Oliver Partridge; transcripts (manuscript and typescript) of letters by Ephraim Williams, Jr. and Caleb Strong; bills and receipts; and a recipe-book of Lydia Ann (Clark) Sergeant.
  - Papers of Erastus Sergeant regarding the disposal of the estate of John Fowler, Tory refugee, 1775-1790 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes receipts, inventories, accounts, promissory notes, and credit orders payable in kind.
  - Indentures, leases, accounts, inventories, and other papers regarding John Fowler's estate, 1780-1782 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Printed material and writings, 1930-1948, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes printed material and newspaper clippings on the history of Stockbridge, Massachusetts; a poem by (Mrs. Theodore) Pamela (Dwight) Sedgwick, titled 'Address to the Bridge from the honorable body of Nations'; and a photograph of an unidentified woman.
  - Letters to Lydia Ann (Clark) Sergeant from George Sergeant, 1846-1848 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence between George Sergeant, Clarissa (Partridge) Sergeant, Catharine (Sergeant) De Forest, and Dr. Henry De Forest, 1842-1850 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence between George Sergeant, Clarissa (Partridge) Sergeant, Catharine (Sergeant) De Forest, and Dr. Henry De Forest, 1842-1861 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Also includes correspondence with Susan (Sereant) Dashiell, George F. De Forest, Sewall Sergeant, Sr., Lydia Ann (Clark) Sergeant, Sewall Sergeant, Jr., F. A. Sergeant, Charles Spencer Sergeant, Cary (Mrs. Elliott) Sergeant, and other family members.
  - Correspondence between George Sergeant, Clarissa (Partridge) Sergeant, Catharine (Sergeant) De Forest, Dr. Henry De Forest, and Elliott Sergeant, 1841-1860 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence between George Sergeant, Clarissa (Partridge) Sergeant, Catharine (Sergeant) De Forest, and Dr. Henry De Forest, 1843-1852 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Also includes correspondence with Frank Fowler, C. A. Ely, and other family members and friends.
  - Correspondence between George Sergeant, Clarissa (Partridge) Sergeant, Catharine (Sergeant) De Forest, and Dr. Henry De Forest, 1815-1848 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Also includes correspondence with Caroline (Sergeant) De Forest, S. H. Colton, Egbert Starr, Lydia Ann (Clark) Sergeant, and other family and friends.
  - Correspondence between George Sergeant, Clarissa (Partridge) Sergeant, Catharine (Sergeant) De Forest, and Dr. Henry De Forest, 1839-1850 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Also includes correspondence between Oliver Partridge and numerous friends, acquaintances, and family members, including E. A. Clarke, S. H. Colton, E. Dewey, Frank Fowler, Joseph Lathrop, Samuel P. Putnam, George W. Root, and Egbert Starr; additional family correspondence among Clarissa (Partridge) Sergeant, Sewall Sergeant Sr., Sewall, Jr., and others; and social invitations to George Sergeant and family members from friends.
  - Letters to George Sergeant from Sewall Sergeant, Sr., Clarissa (Partridge) Sergeant, Sewall Sergeant, Jr., Caroline (Sergeant) De Forest, Elliott Sergeant, George F. De Forest, Alfred H. Dashiell, S. H. Colton, Joseph Lathrop, E. B. and William Williams, and other associates, 1821-1852 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters to George Sergeant from Sewall Sergeant, Sr., Clarissa (Partridge) Sergeant, Sewall Sergeant, Jr., Caroline (Sergeant) De Forest, Elliott Sergeant, George F. De Forest, Alfred H. Dashiell, S. H. Colton, Joseph Lathrop, E. B. and William Williams, and other associates, 1845-1856 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Also includes correspondence with Dr. Oliver Partridge, Susan (Sergeant) Dashiell, Edwin A. Clark, Frank and Henry Fowler, James O. Root, Frances Searle, J. M. Whitcomb, Lydia Ann (Clark) Sergeant, and Ely family members.
  - George Sergeant correspondence and invitations, 1840s (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes letters to George Sergeant from Clarissa (Partridge) Sergeant and Joseph Lathrop, as well as social invitations to George Sergeant from friends and acquaintances.
  - George Sergeant correspondence, 1840-1849 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - George Sergeant American Tract Society membership certificate, 1849 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Lydia Ann (Clark) Sergeant correspondence, 1852-1857 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Includes letters to Lydia Ann (Clark) Sergeant from Catharine M. Clark and Emma (Mrs. Marvin M.) French.
  - Catharine M. Clark letters from Lydia Ann (Clark) Sergeant, 1853-1855 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant, Emma (Mrs. Marvin M.) French, and Clarissa (Partridge) Sergeant letters, 1814-1854 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Includes letters to Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant (born 1848) from Catharine (Kate) (Sergeant) De Forest and T. Searilt [?]; letters to Emma (Mrs. Marvin M.) French from Lydia Ann (Clark) Sergeant; and letters to Clarissa (Partridge) Sergeant from Sewall Sergeant, Sr. and George Sergeant.
  - Letters to Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant, Mary Louise Sergeant, and George Sergeant, 1843-1875 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Includes letters to Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant from Charles Spencer Sergeant and Elliott Sergeant; letters to Mary Louise Sergeant from Sewall Sergeant, Jr.; and letters to George Sergeant from E. R. Williams.
  - Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant letters from Charles Spencer Sergeant, 1872-1875 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant letters from Mary Louise (Mollie) Sergeant, 1869-1871 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant letters from Mary Louise (Mollie) Sergeant and George Sergeant, 1866-1872 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant correspondence, 1857-1875 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Includes letters from Carrie H. Sergeant, "Nellie" Sergeant, Catharine (Sergeant) De Forest, Margaret Dickey, George Sergeant, and Mary Louise (Mollie) Sergeant. Also includes letters to Lydia Ann (Clark) Sergeant and Catharine (Sergeant) De Forest.
  - Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant letters from Catharine (Sergeant) De Forest and Mary Louise (Mollie) Sergeant, 1874 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant letters from Charles Spencer Sergeant, 1873-1875 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant and George Sergeant letters from Mary Louise (Mollie) Sergeant and Catharine (Sergeant) De Forest, 1866-1875 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant and George Sergeant letters from Mary Louise (Mollie) Sergeant, 1867-1874 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant school reports, 1856-1857 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - George Sergeant, Lydia Ann (Clark) Sergeant, Catharine (Sergeant) De Forest, and Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant letters, 1843-1869 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Includes letters to George Sergeant, Lydia Ann (Clark) Sergeant, and Catharine (Sergeant) De Forest from Clarissa (Partridge) Sergeant. Also includes letters to George Sergeant and Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant from C. A. Ely.
  - Lydia Ann (Clark) Sergeant and Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant letters, 1844-1874 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Includes letters to Lydia Ann (Clark) Sergeant from Caroline (Sergeant) De Forest. Also includes letters to Lydia Ann (Clark) Sergeant and Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant from Susan (Sergeant) and Alfred Dashiell.
  - Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant, Mary Louise (Mollie) Sergeant, and Clarissa (Partridge) Sergeant letters, 1861-1873 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Includes letters to Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant and Mary Louise (Mollie) Sergeant from Catharine (Sergeant) De Forest. Also includes letters to Catharine De Forest Sergeant and Clarissa (Partridge) Sergeant from Mary Louise Sergeant and letters to Mary Louise Sergeant from George Sergeant.
  - Mary Louise and Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant, George Sergeant, Lydia Ann (Clark), and Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant letters, 1864-1874 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Includes letters to Mary Louise and Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant from George Sergeant and Sewall Sergeant, Jr. Also includes letters to George Sergeant, Lydia Ann (Clark), and Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant from Catharine (Sergeant) De Forest.
  - Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant letters, 1859-1880 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Includes letters to Catharine (Kitty) De Forest Sergeant from Catharine and Martha P. Clark and other family members.
  - Diaries and notebooks, 1845-1848 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Includes a diary by an unidentified writer, 1845; an account book by an unidentified writer, 1848; and an undated inventory book and undated notebook by unidentified writers.
  - Typescripts and photostats of Sergeant correspondence, 1754, 1832-1845 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Includes copies of letters by Clarissa (Partridge) Sergeant, Caroline (Sergeant) De Forest, Charles Spencer Sergeant, and Abigail (Williams) Sergeant Dwight (died 1791).
  - "Some Old Letters Relating to Early Stockbridge, 1749-1754", 1895 February (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Reprint from Scribner's Magazine, 16 pages.
  - Katharine (Sergeant) Angell White letters from Caroline Belle Sergeant, 1944-1953 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
  - Katharine (Sergeant) Angell White letters from Marjorie Rose Ryan, 1751 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Includes a photostat of a letter by Abigail (Williams) Sergeant Dwight.
  - Katharine (Sergeant) Angell White letters from Caroline Belle Sergeant, 1938-1954 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
- Additional material
  Additional Sergeant family papers, etc., bequethed to Yale University under the will of Katharine S. White and received by Manuscripts and Archives, Sterling Memorial Library, June 1978.
  - Photographs of Sergeant family members, including Bessie B. Shepley, Katharine Sergeant, and Charles Sergeant, 1879-1918, Undated; 1879-1918 (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
  - Resolution from the board members at the Hampshire County Trust Company to the family of George H. Shepley expressing their sorrow at his passing, 1923-04-20 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - George Sergeant's declaration of love to Lydia A. Clark and her reply, 1846-01-30 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Mortgage deeds, discharges, and an insurance policy, 1863-03-1873-02 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Mary Sergeant letters, 1860-1868 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Includes seventeen letters from Mary Sergeant, August 1861-October 1868 and two letters to Mary Sergeant, August 1861-May 1866. Also includes one letter to George Sergeant, January 3, 1860.
  - Letters to Mrs. William Heinsdale from Sergeant family members, June 1848-January 1861 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Includes fifteen letters to Mrs. William Heinsdale from Lydia, Kittie, and other Sergeant family members.
  - Letters to Lydia Sergeant and George Sergeant, 1847-1864 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Includes forty-seven letters to Lydia Sergeant from her father, S. Clark, and others, August 1847-March 1860. Also includes nine letters to George Sergeant, March 1852-January 1864.
  - Letters to George Sergeant, 1858-1861 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - "Address to the Bride" poem, written by Mrs. Theodore Sedgwick, Undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Covenant to God written by Spencer Clark (died in Northampton), 1955-04-10 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Letters to Kittie Sergeant, July 1852-September 1868 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Includes twenty-three letters to Kittie Sergeant from Winnie and Nellie (her nieces?), Cousin Elsends, and other family members.
  - Will of Oliver Partridge, 1825 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Letters to Kitty and Mary Sergeant, August 1848-September 1858 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Sergeant family letters and writings, April 1847-June 1860 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Includes seven letters written by various members of the Sergeant family and a poem, titled "The Farmer," written by Kittie.
  - Book belonging to Lydia H. Clark containing poems and quotes, Undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Copy of a map of Niagara Falls, Undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Supplement to The Independent, 1864-10-06 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Notes on books and manuscripts in an unidentified hand, Undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Mrs. George Sergeant's calling card, Undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Letters to Charles S. Sergeant, April 1905-July 1907 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    Includes twenty-five business letters to Charles S. Sergeant and one letter from his sister, "Puss."
  - Business documents of Charles S. Sergeant, 1902-1905 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - "Historical Pageant of Northhampton, Mass., 1911" (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Letters to Rosamond and Katharine Sergeant, December 1903 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Business letters to Charles S. Sergeant, 1904-01-1911-04 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Letters to Charles S. Sergeant from his mother and other correspondents, December 1903-April 1905 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Letter to Elizabeth Sergeant, April 8, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Letters to Charles S. Sergeant and "Miss" Sergeant, June 1904-January 1905 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    Includes fifty-four letters to Charles S. Sergeant from his daughter Elsie and other correspondents. Also includes a letter to "Miss" Sergeant.
  - Letters to Charles S. Sergeant, December 1903-June 1905 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    Includes twenty-seven letters to Charles S. Sergeant from Elsie, "Puss," and other correspondents.
  - Letters to Charles S. Sergeant and Katharine Sergeant, March 1904-Janury 1905 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    Includes sixty letters to Charles S. Sergeant from Elsie, "Puss," and others. Also includes a letter to Katharine Sergeant.
  - Photograph album, 1800s and early 1900s (Box 4, Folder 33)
    Includes two loose photographs, inserted.
  - Photograph album, 1800s and early 1900s (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Family portraits and photographs, early and mid 1900s (Box 4, Folder 35-42)
  - Family photographs, 1800s and early 1900s (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Family portraits and photographs, 1800s and 1900s (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Family daguerreotypes (Box 5)
    Includes thirty-two daguerreotypes of members of the Sergeant family.